ERIC GRIMSON: Now that we've
added functions to our
armamentarium of tools, we're
going to see that that gives
us a lot of power in terms of
thinking about computational
ways of tackling problems.
Functions give us, as we said,
that ability to abstract, to
capture a computation and then
wrap it up as if it were a
primitive, gives the user the
ability to treat a function
like a black box.
You suppress the details and
you just use the contract,
that specification that says,
if you give me things that
satisfy certain constraints,
this function will give you
back answers that meet
particular desires.
That's great.
But even functions can come
in different flavors.
And there's some real power to
thinking about different ways
of tackling a computational
problem.
And I wanted to spend a little
bit of time in this section
talking about that.
Let's start with what
we've seen so far.
We've really been using looping
constructs as our way
of building algorithms.
And those looping constructs,
things like while loop, a for
loop, lead naturally to what we
would refer to as iterative
algorithms.
They iterate their way through
the loop, going over and over
the same computation with
slight changes.
And in particular, we can
think of an iterative
algorithm as capturing
computation in a set of what
we could call state variables.
These are variables that
describe the state of the
computation.
And those variables update or
change their values on each
iteration through the loop.
Let's look at an example.
So here's a simple
little example.
Imagine that we want to do
multiplication, and we're
going to do it just using
successive addition.
Our computer only comes
with addition.
It doesn't come with a
built in multiply.
I know that's dumb, but
it gives us a simple
example to deal with.
If we wanted to do that, to do
multiplication by successive
additions, then a simple way to
think about it is to say if
we want to multiply a by b,
we're just going to add a to
itself b times.
And iteratively, what
does that mean?
Literally, we could say
computation's going to be
captured by two variables.
One is the iteration number.
Which time through
the loop am I at?
That number, let's call it i,
arbitrarily, is going to
start off at b.
And the second thing we're
going to need is a state
variable that captures
how many additions
we've already done.
What the result is so far.
Let's just call it result.
So that's the current state
of the computation.
And that starts off at zero.
So notice, each of these
state variables has an
initialization.
We started off somewhere.
And then we think of the
computation as iterating
through or updating those
state variables.
And those update rules, in this
case, would be that on
each iteration i, my iteration
number, is going to reduce by
one and result, the thing
that's holding the
computation, is going to take
the current value of result,
add the value of a to it, and
that becomes the new value of
that state variable.
So these state variables have
the property that if I stop
the computation at any
point, they tell me
exactly where I am.
And they have the property
that not only are they
initialized, but at least one of
them will have a condition
for telling me when
I can stop.
And in this case, I'll stop
when the iteration count
gets down to 0.
I know I've done all the
things I need to do.
We've seen examples like that,
but this idea of iteration is
nicely captured.
And if we put it into code, in
fact, we see something that
very nicely builds on that.
We initialize one
state variable.
In this case, we're going to
just use the parameter passed
in as the other state
variable.
And it's initialized when
it is passed in.
And then the loop simply
has updates.
There's the updating of
those state variables.
And let me make a simple comment
about this format,
since we haven't
used it before.
That format is the same as
saying let result be bound to
result plus a.
And this one is saying let
b be bound to b minus 1.
It's simple, little shorthand
for doing that kind of
computation.
And of course, when I'm
done, I'm going
to return the result.
We've seen these kinds
of examples before.
And you can see how iteration's
a nice way of
thinking about it.
That loop actually captures what
the changes in the state
variables are at each point.
And if we wanted to try it,
we could certainly go
over here to Python.
And there is my definition
of iterMul.
And if I load it into an IDLE
environment, then I can
certainly say things like,
give me the iterative
multiplication of 3 and 5, and
it does the right thing.
And I can even be more fancy
about it and say things like--
And it does it pretty quickly.
We haven't shown out the
intermediate stages of the
loop, but you've seen enough
examples of this to realize
that it is, in fact, doing that
counting down of b while
accumulating the results
in result and then
returning the value.
Great.